{
    "tossups": [
        {
            "question": "A ruler of this dynasty, nicknamed \u201cthe Brilliant,\u201d created a code of laws called the Regulations of the Royal Court and used the execution of a prince called Chuban as a pretext to rebel against Abu Sa\u2019id Khan. Despite his nickname of \u201cthe Great\u201d, a ruler of this non-Macedonian dynasty named Alexander disintegrated his kingdom after he appointed his three sons as co-rulers and abdicated to become a monk. With help from local Kipchaks, a ruler of this dynasty leading monaspa calvary encircled a Seljuk army, aided by the title mountain, at the Battle of (*) Didgori. The upper classes of this dynasty, called the \u200beristavi and aznauri, were at the top of the patronqmoba\u200b feudal system. This dynasty ruled three kingdoms of Kakheti, Imerti, and Kartli after their country fractured under invasions from the Mongols and Timurids.\u00a0 For 10 points, identify this dynasty, whose members like Tamar the Great and David the Builder ruled medieval Georgia.",
            "answer": "Bagrationi (accept Georgian Bragatids or Bragations)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A member of this family decries the Japanese as \u201csandal-wearing goldfish-tenders\u201d after accusing an employee of stealing from him. That member of this family had earlier held a dance where he demanded that the band add a fourth beat to the \u201cBlue Danube Waltz\u201d, the resulting confusion of which allows another character to escape with his slave Virgil. A member of this family is shown laughing in the shower, church, and while asleep after reminiscing about crippling an Irish laborer with a bumper car in his youth. That member of this family uses \u201cglower power\u201d to scare off a group of hippies protesting his (*) germ warfare research facility. After a member of this family abandoned it as a child, a teddy bear named Bobo is owned by Charles Lindbergh and Hitler before being found by Bart Simpson. For 10 points, identify this family whose most famous member owns the Springfield Nuclear Power Plant.",
            "answer": "Burns family (accept Mr. Burns; accept Charles Montgomery Burns; accept Wainwright Montgomery Burns)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The lyrics to an unofficial national anthem of this country were apocryphally written in response to their author witnessing a foreign soldier beating up a shopkeeper. A foreign power increased the capacity of an important railroad in this country by connecting it to the Karun River. Prior to his service at the Battle of Monte Cassino, Wojtek, a Syrian brown bear, was \u201crecruited\u201d by the exiled Polish Anders\u2019 Army as it passed through this country. To ensure control of this country\u2019s (*) oil and supply lines, an Anglo-Soviet invasion of this country deposed its ruler and installed his son in Operation Countenance. Operation Long Jump was a Nazi attempt to assassinate the \u201cBig Three\u201d at a conference in this country. For 10 points, name this country which hosted the Tehran Conference.",
            "answer": "Iran (accept Persia)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A city was renamed after a leader of this country-specific party after he negotiated the creation of the VAZ automobile plant. That leader of this party was shot three times by a fascist student in 1948, but survived. Meliorism was a faction of this party, and in 1977 a member of this party, Luciano Lama, denounced the autonomist movement. In 1991, this party dissolved itself in a \u201cturning point\u201d and re-formed as the Democratic Party of the Left. Under the leadership of Enrico (*) Berlinguer, it entered into a \u201cHistoric Compromise\u201d with a Christian Democratic party from 1976 to 1980. This party was the largest of its kind in post-WWII western Europe, and after one of its founders was jailed in 1926, he formulated concepts such as the subaltern and cultural hegemony in his Prison Notebooks. For 10 points, name this organization that was led by Palmiro Togliatti and Antonio Gramsci, a Marxist-Leninist party.",
            "answer": "Italian Communist Party (accept Partita Comunista Italiano, accept PCI, accept equivalents mentioning \u201cCommunism\u201d and \u201cItaly\u201d. The city is Tolyatti in Russia.)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Information detailing the boundaries, landscape, and history of the land in and around this kingdom, while common knowledge for its residents, was held in secret for outsiders in books known as kadaim. In recognition of Dutch assistance against another European power, Vimala Dharma Suriya I of this kingdom supposedly said \u201c[this kingdom] is now Flanders\u201d after meeting with Joris van Spilbergen. An object most commonly associated with this kingdom was under the care of the position of Diyawadana Nilame. The (*) Uva Rebellion sought to reverse the 1815 annexation of this kingdom. This kingdom came to power after the fall of the Kingdom of Kotte and was the last major native state in its region before British rule. For 10 points, what is this Sri Lankan kingdom famous for holding a tooth of the Buddha?",
            "answer": "Kingdom of Kandy",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The HMS Raccoon was part of an expedition sent to take a fort in this modern state during the War of 1812, but arrived to find that the fort had already been sold to a British company. A disagreement over the payment of a horse between the Wasco man Cockstock and the freed black man James Saules was an important factor in two separate laws banning African-Americans from moving to this modern state. Political organization in this modern state developed out of a series of \u201cwolf meetings\u201d held in its town of Champoeg (\u201csham-poo\u201d-ee). It\u2019s not Hawaii, but the chief Naukane was sent by (*) Kamehameha I to look after Hawaiians traveling on the Tonquin to a fort in this modern state. Built to facilitate trapping in the area, Fort Astoria was the first American settlement in this modern state. For 10 points, what is this modern state whose Willamette Valley was the endpoint of a namesake trail?",
            "answer": "Oregon (accept Oregon Territory or Oregon Country)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A council called to support this belief was later called the \u201cHeadless Council\u201d because no church officials of sufficient importance were in attendance. A governor, whom some later sources simply called \u201cthe Dragon\u201d to liken him to the beasts of the Book of Revelation, allegedly forced monks and nuns to marry each other in a stadium to stifle opposition to this belief. An argument levied against this belief was the miraculous appearance of acheiropoieta. Much of Calabria and Sicily was removed from papal authority after (*) Pope Gregory III convened two synods in Rome in the same year to oppose this belief. St. Catherine\u2019s Monastery in Egypt contains many works that were unaffected by this belief, including an early mosaic of Christ Pantocrator. For 10 points, identify this belief, most famously held by Byzantine Emperor Leo III, that seeks the destruction of religious imagery.",
            "answer": "Byzantine iconoclasm",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A later Incan story claims that the extensive systems for acquiring this resource at Pikillaqta (\u201cpee-keel\u201d-YAHK-tah) were created for the hand of the maiden Sumac Tica. Robert Bradley has argued that the lack of this resource at the site of Kuelap (KWAY-lap) suggests that it was not a fortress, but rather a settlement for elites that was supplied by nearby villages. Control over this resource is what defined local social hierarchies, now called parcialidades, throughout much of Pre-Columbian Peru. The Nazca Culture constructed underground puquios to store this resource. The suka qullu (\u201csue\u201d-kah \u201ccool-you\u201d) system used this resource to keep (*) crops insulated from freezing temperatures. With corn, this resource is used to make chicha. As well as keeping soil in place, the use of and\u00e9n (ahn-DAYN) terraces kept this resource from flowing down hillsides. For 10 points, name this resource gathered from places like the Moche River and Lake Titicaca.",
            "answer": "water",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A lavish tent that was to host an important ceremony during an event in this city was burnt down during the rehearsal by a cigarette butt, requiring a new one to be hastily made. A series of military exercises in this city is one of two extant portions of a Kinemacolor film made by Charles Urban. Plans for George VI to impress the \u201cnative minds\u201d of this city by traveling to it via plane to hold a grand ceremony at Coronation Park were dropped because of their lack of political or financial tact. A royal proclamation given in this city announced the reversal of the first (*) Partition of Bengal. The construction of a new section of this city by Edward Lutyens began during a 1911 durbar [duhr-\u201cBAR\u201d] celebrating the accession of George V. For 10 points, identify this city, the last capital of the British Raj and the current one of India.",
            "answer": "New Delhi\u00a0",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "One designer of these things left CDC after the STAR-100 project stalled. One model of these things had a \u201cwaterfall\u201d cooling system that used Fluorinert. A company that produces these things was acquired by SGI, and that company developed the Y-MP and X-MP models under the oversight of Steve Chen. The LINPACK test is conducted on these things, and Gordon and Comet are located in a \u201ccenter\u201d for these things in UC San Diego. These things are ranked by the (*) TOP500 list, and some of these objects engineered by Seymour Cray have a C-shaped design. Several of these things have broken the Pentascale barrier. Examples of these objects include Atlas and ILLIAC, and the performance of these things is often measured in FLOPs, or Floating-point Operations per Second. For 10 points, name these objects, some of which include IBM\u2019s Deep Blue and Watson.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Supercomputers (prompt on \u201cComputers\u201d; do not accept or prompt on \u201cPC\u201d or \u201cPersonal Computer\u201d)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Fortifications that once defended this city included Gu\u00eenes and Hammes. At the Battle of Ludford Bridge, a \u201cMaster Porter\u201d from this city, Andrew Trollope, defected to the Lancastrians. In the wake of that battle, a future king fled with the Nevilles to this city. The Earl of Warwick was a \u201ccaptain\u201d of this city. After the loss of this city to the Duke of Guise in 1558, Mary I reportedly said that when she was buried, she would have this city (*) \u201clying in her heart\u201d. After the Treaty of Br\u00e9tigny, a namesake \u201cPale\u201d was set up around this city, which was a center of medieval wool imports from England. In the wake of the Battle of Cr\u00e9cy, Edward III captured this city, but spared its inhabitants after six of its prominent citizens volunteered for execution. For 10 points, name this northern French port city, whose \u201cBurghers\u201d were commemorated in a Rodin sculpture.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Calais",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "His response to a Mongol invasion of this modern country earned a ruler of one kingdom the epithet \u201che who flees from the \u2018Turk\u2019\u201d. After Felipe de Brito used his governorship of the city of Syriam to make a de facto independent pirate state, a ruler of a kingdom in this modern country massacred the Portuguese settlers at Dianga to prevent further betrayals. Following his defeat at the Battle of Khajwa, Shah Shuja fled to a kingdom in this modern country, where conflict over his wealth with King Sanda Thudhamma led to Shuja\u2019s death. (*) Maung Htaw Lay was an influential official in this modern country who protected its Shwedagon Pagoda from British troops using it as a fort. Following the Sepoy Rebellion, Bahadur Shah II was exiled to Rangoon in, for 10 points, what modern country that formed the easternmost portion of British India?",
            "answer": "Burma (accept Myanmar)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Yuko Hakateyama slit her throat as an act of penance for Japan after one of her fellow countrymen attempted to assassinate an official from this country. In an attempt to free a diplomat from this country, prominent merchant Takadaya Kahei was captured by Peter Rikord in 1812. The merchant Dembei was the first Japanese person to travel to the capital of this country. The first official agreement between Japan and this country was the Treaty of Shimoda. It\u2019s not China, but the Treaty of (*) San Francisco has fueled an ongoing dispute between Japan and this country over islands such as Etorofu and Kunashiri. This country suffered a massive defeat at the hands of the Japanese Navy at the Battle of Tsushima. For 10 points, name this country who still disputes ownership of the Kuril Islands with Japan.",
            "answer": "Russian Empire",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Description acceptable\u00a0 After a leader in this event expressed distaste for doves, \u201cPrincess of Porcelain\u201d Helen Boehm created a sculpture of two mute swans called The Bird of Peace, which was gifted during this event. Max Frankel won a Pulitzer Prize for his coverage of this event. Winston Lord was cut out of pictures of a meeting during this event to avoid embarrassing a high-ranking official who was excluded from it. This event was arranged through both sides relations with (*) Yahya Khan\u2019s government. This event resulted in the issuing of the first of the Three Communiqu\u00e9s. A meeting between Glenn Cowan and Zhu\u0101ng Z\u00e9d\u00f2ng was the start of \u201cping pong diplomacy\u201d, which began the year before this event. For 10 points, identify this 1972 event in which the 37th president of the US traveled to the world\u2019s most populous country.",
            "answer": "Richard M. Nixon\u2019s visit to China (accept any answer that says that Nixon is in China)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A punitive naval raiding expedition during this man\u2019s reign may have aided the Slavic siege of Patras. After a protracted theological debate with this man and multiple imprisonments, some sources claim that the seventh Shi\u2019a Imam, M\u016bsa ibn Ja\u2019far al-K\u0101zim, was poisoned by this man. Though quickly ignored, a peace term after this man\u2019s second large campaign against the Byzantines was the imposition of the jizya on Emperor Nikephoros I and his son. This ruler split his lands between his sons (*) al-Mu\u2019min and al-Amin, setting the stage for the Fourth Fitna. As well as destroying the political power of the Barmakids, this ruler sent a mechanical clock and the elephant Abul-Abbas as gifts to Charlemagne. For 10 points, identify this man, an Abbasid Caliph in the late 8th century who features prominently in the One Thousand and One Nights.",
            "answer": "Harun ar-Rashid (accept Harun al-Rashid)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Statutes promulgated by this leader at Thionville and Abbeville reorganized his army into troops \u201cof the ordinance\u201d. This leader\u2019s territorial expansions included buying Guelders from its duke Arnold and Ferrette from Archduke Sigismund of Austria. After slaughtering the garrison of Grandson despite its capitulation, this leader lost the Battle of Murat when his troops were caught by surprise while collecting their pay. This leader regained the territories of Boulogne and Ponthieu after the Treaty of Conflans. After this leader\u2019s death, his daughter (*) Mary the Rich married the Holy Roman Emperor Maximilian I. This leader\u2019s conflicts with the Duke of Lorraine, Ren\u00e9 II, led to a battle in which he and his army were obliterated by Swiss mercenaries near Metz. For 10 points, name this son of Philip the Good and Duke of Burgundy, who died at the Battle of Nancy.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Charles the Bold",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Competing with Perkins & Co, who imported this good from the Ottoman Empire, Russel and Company became the biggest seller of it in one country during the mid-19th century. During the 18th century, a plainer form of this good in a paste called yapian replaced a mixed form called madak. The production of heimi or \u201cblack rice\u201d, a form for this good, flourished during the early 20th century despite its labor intensity. A lack of local demand for European products led to the trade of this good, sourced from colonies in (*) India, for silver from private smugglers; this silver was then used to buy goods like tea and silk in Canton for export. After the destruction of 1,000 tons of this good by an Imperial Commissioner in Humen as contraband in 1839 and skirmishes at Kowloon, Lord Palmerston sent an expedition to blockade the Pearl River. For 10 points, name this good, a narcotic which names two conflicts between the Q\u012bng Dynasty and the United Kingdom.",
            "answer": "opium",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "An allegorical map shows the ideals of this movement in the lands north of the \u201cDemarcation Mountains\u201d, which separates them from places like the \u201cRat Soup\u201d and \u201cPenitentiary\u201d Rivers. In 1850, P.T. Barnum\u2019s American Museum put on over 100 performances of a play in support of this movement. It\u2019s not necessarily related to San Francisco, but a Committee of Fifty met to examine the claims put forward by a branch of an institution supporting this movement led by Mary Hunt. A statue in Washington, D.C. featuring a heron and two intertwined dolphins was donated by Henry Cogswell, a supporter of this movement, and originally dispensed (*) ice water. A riot against a law passed in support of this movement was put down by activist and mayor of Portland, Maine, Neal Dow. One reformer advocated for this movement through \u201chatchetations\u201d. For 10 points, what was this movement that sought to curb the consumption of alcohol?",
            "answer": "temperance (accept prohibition or other descriptive answers)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "One leader of a conspiracy in this country was inspired by the Encyclop\u00e9die to draw up plans for a class-free republic and later drowned after the San Pedro de Alcantara was shipwrecked. This country, site of the Conspiracy of the Three Antonios, was the birthplace of an independence leader who was the illegitimate son of a man who had earlier been created as \u201cBaron of Ballinar\u201d and appointed as royal governor of this country. Forces led by Juan Jos\u00e9 Carrera were defeated by Mariano Osorio at the Disaster of Rancagua, ending this country\u2019s (*) Patria Vieja period. This country gained its independence after victories at the battles of Maip\u00fa and Chacabuco. The first colonial governor of this country, Pedro de Valdivia, was killed in a battle against the Mapuche. For 10 points, name this South American country whose independence leaders included Bernardo O\u2019Higgins.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Chile",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "According to one author, uris were elephant-sized bulls that attacked any living thing they saw, which lived in the forests beyond this river. Ammianus Marcellinus described the raid of a city on this river in 368 CE by the chieftain Rando. In his writings, Gregory of Tours moved the site of the martyrdom of the possibly mythical Theban Legion from Agaunum in modern Switzerland to Colonia Agrippensium, a city on this river. Roman settlement along this river is currently exhibited in the archaeological park of (*) Xanten, which had earlier been besieged by the forces of Gaius Julius Civilis during the Batavian Revolt. Two bridges were constructed across this river by Julius Caesar to intimidate hostile tribes like the Suebi who lived on its eastern shore. For 10 points, what is this river, which marked the farthest extent of Roman control of Germania?",
            "answer": "Rhine River (accept Rhenus River)",
            "category": "History"
        }
    ],
    "bonuses": []
}